International Silver Company Records
© 2004 University of Connecticut
International Silver Company Records.
undated, 1853-1931.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
International Silver Company.
48 linear feet.
MSS19800008
The International Silver Company was organized under the laws of the State of New Jersey on November 19, 1898. Within the next year, seventeen companies were purchased. By the early 1900s, it had become a large industrial corporation. Its operations centered at Meriden, Connecticut, would prove to be the major producer of silver products in the United States.
History
The International Silver Company was organized under the laws of the State of New Jersey on 19 November 1898. Immediately upon organization, the company bought the total capital stock of the following companies: Barbour Silver Company (Hartford), *Holmes & Edwards Silver Company (Bridgeport), *Manhattan Silver Plate, (Lyons, New York), *Meriden Britannia Company (Meriden), *Norwich Cutlery (Norwich), *William Rogers Manufacturing Company (Hartford), Rogers Cutlery (Hartford), Rogers and Brothers (Waterbury), Rogers and Hamilton (Waterbury), Wilcox Silver Plate (Meriden), Watrous Manufacturing Company (Wallingford), Standard Silver Company, Ltd. (Toronto, Canada).
During the first six months of 1899, an additional four companies were purchased. Derby Silver Company (Derby), Simpson, Hall, Miller & Company (Wallingford), Simpson Nickel Company (Wallingford), Middletown Plate Company (Middletown).
In January of 1903, the stock of the United States Silver Corporation was acquired, thereby gaining indirect ownership of: *C. Rogers & Brothers (Meriden).
Thus, in the space of a few years, there came into being a large industrial corporation, worth $20,000,000 at organization, which, with its operations centered at Meriden, Connecticut, would prove to be the major producer of silver products in the United States.
(*) indicates companies represented in this collection.
Scope and Content
With only a few exceptions, the collection consists of bound volumes of financial records and other materials relating to the business of silver products manufacturing in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The record is by no means complete. In addition to financial matters, researchers may find materials of interest to broader social history in the Rogers Manufacturing Company correspondence volumes, and the time records and advertisements of the Meriden Britannia Company.
Arrangement
Series I: Meriden Britannia Company ( undated, 1853-1899 ) consists of 38 volumes including financial records (blotters, cashbooks, ledgers, and indices), time records, advertisements/catalogues, and memoranda. Although gaps appear in the cashbook collection, nonetheless, a reasonably complete record is provided in this category for the period 1853-1874, with an additional volume for 1893-1899.
Series II: Rogers Manufacturing Company ( undated, 1885-1900 ), consists of 16 volumes of financial records (ledgers and journals), records of the New York store, correspondence, and one volume of electrotypes illustrating Rogers' products. As mentioned above, the correspondence is illustrative of the business conditions of the period and consists of copies of outgoing letters from the company officers.
Series III: Other ISC Predecessors ( ca. 1880-1901 ), consists of a few volumes from four companies which later became part of International Silver: Manhattan Silver Plate Company, (1 volume, cash book 1880s), Holmes and Edwards Silver Company, (1 volume, scrapbook, 1890s) Norwich Cutlery Company, (2 volumes, cashbook and daybook, 1890s), and C. Rogers and Brothers, (1 volume, private ledger, 1899-1901).
Series IV: International Silver Company ( undated, 1899-1931 ), consists of 4 volumes from the early years of the company including order books and circulars.
Series V: Unidentified Volumes ( undated, 1875-1906 ), consists of 8 volumes of material which cannot be identified as to origin. It appears that much of this may be from Meriden Britannia, but precise identification has not been possible.
Series VI: Non-ISC Volumes ( undated, 1899-1916 ), consists of 5 volumes from silver manufacturing companies which do not appear to have been a part of International Silver Company. Represented here are Oneida Community Silver Company, (2 scrapbooks, 1910s, from the publications Jewelers Circular and Keystone), Maltby Henley Company, (2 volumes of financial records, 1900s), and E. G. Webster & Son, (1 volume of electrotypes, undated).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
Silver industry--Connecticut.; Silver industry--New York (State); Silver-plated flatware--United States.; Silverware--United States.; New York (State)--Business, industries, and trades--Silver.; Lyons (N.Y.); Connecticut--Business, industries, and trades--Silver.; Meriden (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Silver.; Hartford (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Silver.; Bridgeport (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Silver.; Norwich (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Silver.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Scrap-Books.; Catalogs.; Indexes.; Advertisements.
Occupations:
Manufacturer of silver products.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred to the University of Connecticut from Yale University in three shipments that were completed on 15 January 1980.
Detailed Description
[The majority of the collection is shelved by volume number, only the volumes with a box number indicated are located in boxes.]
- Series I: Meriden Britannia Company, undated, 1853-1899
  - Blotters
    - #16, 1860-1863 (Box 1:, Volume 1)
    - #[18], 1868-1869 (Box 1:, Volume 2)
    - #20, 1870-1871 (Box 1:, Volume 3)
    - #21, 1872 (Box 1:, Volume 4)
  - Cash Books
    - 1853 January (Box 1:, Volume 5)
    - 1853 - 1857 July (Volume 6-11)
    - 1865 August - 1868 November (Volume 12-17)
    - 1869 May - October (Volume 18)
    - 1870 March - September (Volume 19)
    - 1871 September - 1872 February (Volume 20)
    - 1874 April - December (Volume 21-22)
    - 1893 January -1899 April (Box 2:, Volume 23)
  - Ledgers
    - 1855-1857 (Volume 24)
    - 1860-1862 (Volume 25)
    - Supply Purchase—Machinery, undated (Box 2:, Volume 26)
    - Early financial volume, 1854-1856 (Volume 27)
  - Indices to Financial Volumes
    - Index to Ledgers EE and FF (Volume 28)
    - Index N-W (Volume 29)
    - Index P (Volume 30)
    - Index U-X (Volume 31)
    - Index Y-Z (Volume 32)
  - Time Records
    - Time Book (includes unbound materials), 1869-1884 (Volume 33)
    - Machine Room Employees, 1872-1878 (Volume 34)
  - Advertisements/Catalogues
    - Catalogue List, 1889-1897 (Volume 35)
    - National Advertisements, 1890 (Box 2:, Volume 36)
    - Contracts for advertising, 1893-1916 (Volume 37)
  - Memoranda
    - Consignment to Chicago store, undated (Volume 38)
  - Order Books
    - 1906 January - 1922 September (Box 3:, Volume 39)
    - 1909 January - 1931 December (Box 3:, Volume 40)
- Series II: Rogers Manufacturing Company, undated, 1885-1900
  - Financial Records
    - Expenditures (includes unbound materials), 1881-1882 (Box 4:, Volume 41)
    - Purchase Ledger, 1893 (Othertype OS, Volume 42)
    - Sales & Purchase Ledger (with index), 1898-1899 (Box 4:, Volume 43)
    - Sales Ledger, 1898-1899 (Othertype OS, Volume 44-45)
    - Journal, 1893-1899 (Volume 46)
    - Account Ledgers, 1893-1899 (Box 3:, Volume 47-48)
  - New York Store
    - Financial Records (includes unbound materials), 1865-1894 (Box 4:, Volume 49)
  - Correspondence
    - “W.H.W.” [W.H. Watrous], 1887-1888 (Box 4:, Volume 50)
    - F. William Rogers, Secretary, 1885-1886 (Box 5:, Volume 51)
    - William Rogers Manufacturing Company, 1890 (Box 4:, Volume 52)
    - William Rogers Manufacturing Company, 1894 (Box 5:, Volume 53)
    - William Rogers Manufacturing Company, 1897-1898 (Box 5:, Volume 54)
    - William Rogers Manufacturing Company, 1898-1899 (Box 4:, Volume 55-56)
    - William Rogers Manufacturing Company, 1899-1900 (Box 4:, Volume 57)
  - Electrotypes
    - Illustrations of Rogers products, undated (Volume 58)
  - Sales Price Books
    - Price Book (includes unbound materials), undated (Box 3:, Volume 59)
- Series III: Other ISC Predecessors, ca. 1880-1901
  - Manhattan Silver Plate Company
    - Cash Book, 1885-1888 (Box 7:, Volume 60)
  - Holmes and Edwards Silver Company
    - Scrapbook, undated, 1891 (Box 7:, Volume 61)
  - Norwich Cutlery Company
    - Cash Book, 1890-1895 (Volume 62)
    - Day Book, 1894-1896 (Volume 63)
  - C. Rogers and Brothers
    - Private Ledger, 1899-1901 (Box 7:, Volume 64)
- Series IV: International Silver Company, undated, 1899-1931
  - Order Books
    - 1901 September -1902 January (Volume 65)
    - “Foreign”, 1908 January - 1909 January (Volume 66)
  - Circulars
    - #1-I through #218-I, 1899-1931 (Box 6:, Volume 67)
    - Letters #599 - #741, 1917-1921 (Box 6:, Volume 68)
- Series V: Unidentified Volumes, undated, 1875-1906
  - Journals
    - 1863 January - 1868 November (Volume 69)
    - 1872 March - 1874 September (Volume 70)
    - 1890 December - 1899 April (Volume 71)
  - Time Records
    - 1894-1900 (Volume 72)
  - Cash Books
    - “EE”, 1875-1876 (Volume 73)
  - Bills Payable
    - 1869-1871 (Volume 74)
  - Index
    - Index volume, undated (Volume 75)
  - Inventories
    - General inventory of machinery, 1906 (Box 3:, Volume 76)
- Series VI: Non-ISC Volumes, undated, 1899-1916
  - Oneida Community Silver Company
    - Scrapbook of advertisements, 1907-1916 (Volume 77)
    - Scrapbook of advertisements, 1907-1916 (Volume 78)
  - Maltby Henley Company
    - Cashbook, 1900-1903 (Box 7:, Volume 79)
    - Financial records, 1899-1903 (Box 7:, Volume 80)
  - E.G. Webster & Sons
    - Electrotypes, undated (Volume 81)